Good morning, ANAC team, what a pleasure to be here
with you today, such a special day
for us to talk about such an important topic,
I bring it here on behalf of the
team of the Superintendence
of people management. here giving us all the
support we have the honor to count
today with Isabela Camargo journalist is
a person I'm a fan I follow her on
Linkedin I think her speech has
touched hearts and minds and we
managed to bring Isabela today to
talk to the agency team about
sustainable productivity
we talked to Isabela yesterday and
explained to her that here at the agency A
Gente has been working with
performance management that we no longer have
frequency control and that now
we agree on results and deliveries with
all people in all layers of the
organization and how important it is for
us to carry out this performance in a
sustainable way, balancing our lives
professional and our personal life And then there is
no one better than her to bring
this subject up to us so I
won't delay here.
you to
interact on the slide and remember to
share the YouTube link later
because this lecture will be recorded
and we want it to reach all the
people of the agency ok guys, great pleasure to be
here with you remembering this
scoundrel Mariana Dal for those who don't
know me forgot to introduce myself at
Isabela it's so happy to be here with
you that I ended up skipping this part
but here's a word for and
I really appreciate your presence
thank you stage is
yours thank you so much Mari for this introduction
good morning to you good morning to everyone who
they are choosing us see we will have
a time together a time when I
Isabela will be the instrument of various
information that as you will
understand Realizing how connected we are
to how much
our attitude can influence not
only our health but the health of those
around us, I did my best here in
this next hour to share as
much information as possible and I hope it
makes sense to you, but that's how it is
I have some slides here that will only help
to illustrate some
things that I'm talking about, some I
'm going to ask you to play with me, ok
So that you can answer later,
feel free now, it's very important that if
you're here with me, you're with me right away.
talk more about this
multitasking attitude that we have is not ah I
'll let Isabela talk about something here
but I need what she's
talking about
now I'm going to explain what this causes in
our health, ok Dona Mariana
So look
and everything else that you want to
share all manifestations
are very welcome so feel free
we will reserve a good time for the
end for us to exchange But if
you want to express yourself during
my presentation, just take your
comment to the platform you
are on, and then Mari also helps me by
filtering and bringing it at the first
opportunity.
are seeing the screen right so
let's see how to achieve our
goals without losses along the way
Isabela But you saying this because we
already know we adults know that for
every choice there are losses Me Whenever
I'm choosing one thing I'm
not choosing others you can
lose several things during our
journey except two
health and relationships
and when I say relationship I'm already
saying relationship with you
relationship with your family
relationship with the people at your
work it was this order ok and
we usually reverse the order
So how to achieve the that you want
because each one has daily goals, monthly,
weekly,
time. how are we going to do
this being responsible, committed but
without prejudice along the way and then Mari is the
following I'm a big fan of all of you
because everyone who puts themselves at the service of
an organization that influences everyone's lives
my deep respect to all of you it
doesn't matter what area you work in and I
can only say this
because more than 20 years ago I started
working with radio and TV I went through the
main radio and TV stations in the
country very passionate very committed a
lot of orgasm
with pride Funny that we don't
likes to talk about no addiction, no
cigarettes, I don't drink, but I work
our mother from heaven, there those who don't
appreciate a schedule full of
commitment but then people I can only
talk about something I lived
So until I live the experience that I
lived
talk for me, talking about
micropus for health maintenance was
something farther from the world, silly, right,
but very passionate, very caloric
I
arrived at ANAC I arrived at the place r what I always wanted to
work on, I arrived at the main
broadcaster in the country when I was
interviewing Fernanda Montenegro, right,
hitting that Bolão what happened to
me
I had a live blackout it's as if your
system fell, you know,
blackout no one else is watching nothing in the
sky it
's like the gps lost signal
this blackout i was talking about the
weather forecast i forgot the name
of my state capital so be
careful with the kind of forgetting
you have one thing i forgot the
house key to another forgot where you live
but that was a consequence my
whole body was
short circuiting let's use
this term
blurred vision
dizziness when you say fusion actually I could
n't see anything because it was a
total blackout right then dizziness nausea
sweating shortness of breath tachycardia
all at the same time So
committed that I am I held the bills
I finished the newspaper I did one more when
the workday was over I went to the psychiatrist
And then I heard from him
Isabela you are experiencing
Burnout Syndrome and I said imagine Doctor I
love what I do and then he said That's why
even
people who love what they do are much
more likely to have The physical
and mental exhaustion that results from
chronic stress at work workplace that was not
successfully managed
what I received from Diagnosis in 2018
today is like this for every 10 people who
are working Look at my little fingers
7 are experiencing some consequence of
stress and three are experiencing the worst
level of stress called Burnout
a Isabela what a silly thing this is a
modern thing you invented the
name to say about the statue of tiredness
not
Burnout syndrome it is a new name for
a very old problem
in 1869 you sir Jorge Miller
wrote a book called América
Nervosres talking about neurasthenia people
who were exhausted and nervous because
of modern civilization
1869 10 Years Before this other Lord
is on the best known side of all of us
T homas Edison invented the
light bulb filament that we know
today so I didn't have an electric light bulb
and there were already people in deep exhaustion
due to modern civilization curious
this is not then
where I'm trying to get
when We chose our profession
and when we we are driven by the passion of
this profession we do not consider the
variables of this profession
that is,
each of us chose his profession
aiming for
the final result
without considering the situations the variables
that will cause adaptive stress that
is positive stress and chronic stress
which is negative stress and
stress people are equal cholesterol
has good and bad is the same as anxiety
has good and bad and when we
talk about stress
this is a very trivialized word
we forget a little bit to look for it the
origin of the word this gentleman is not
Walt Disney he has this Mouse in his hand
he is the austrian endocrinologist
ranelli he was the one who brought it the term of
physics for our daily life saying
that the effort of adaptation that our
organism
makes to deal with situations that affect
the internal balance is
called stress
He brought this term from physics to a
situation that has existed since the time of the
caves It's been since when our
ancestors were there in the caves and
mammals appeared larger than us, the
body released a hormone called
cortisol For you to face or
run away from this threat, it's
just that people this is a natural response
of the body to some situation that
represents a threat So it's like this People If
we were here in a nice room
at ANAC, pay attention If you have
multi-tasking for a little bit
And then Mari appears a cockroach in the middle
of our meeting
there are people who will run away from the
cockroach and there are people like me who go there
and kill cockroaches
the place grew, right people, so I
always dealt with cockroaches, you too but you were
going to run or without killing the cockroach and kill the
cockroach ready and you m people here who
would rush to work noticed the same
situation can provoke
different reactions so throughout our day
regardless of the profession we are going to
deal with unforeseen adversities with
situations all day long that may or may not
cause adaptive or chronic stress it
is easy to understand this super
for that I need to show you that
the more
tired and exhausted the more extreme
our reasoning becomes, the worse
our reactions are So how come we
are full of tasks Yes all of us,
some more and some a little
less when Mari told me that you
have a lot of autonomy and
flexibility
people who don't want it Autonomist
with stability
This is anyone's dream is it not
I have professional stability and
I have flexibility of autonomy together
so they trust what I do
but we can't
live
with excess trust I will
explain more about it so two
things an We want to follow you I
need you to know What's the difference
between tiredness and exhaustion you
're tired rest ok it's
been a busy week Rested on the
weekend monday ok
exhaustion is different no exhaustion you
rest and
you're still tired you go on vacation and come back angry
So when you're tired You
need to rest when you're
exhausted you need to change your lifestyle it
's that simple and then after this
analysis you will understand if you are
sad or if you are depressed
depressed then we need to
organize the ideas around of these
terms
accepting a situation is a fact
you are following me whether you
like it or not like it or not turning your nose up or
not Brazil is the most anxious country in the world
and then pathological anxiety is not That
anxiety that moves us just like
stress what moves us is not what
paralyzes us is the second most stressed in the
world and the fifth most depressive in the
world
but half a million people were
away from work due to
mental illness in 2020
ah Isabela
I love it when they say that you know Maria
Inácio have any comments like that
in the chat you tell me Why did the
English Prime Minister Wilson
Churchill have nothing to do
he dealt with depression publicly and
I Chico Anysio was the one who asked
the Brazilian Association of Psychiatry for a
term to define this phobia that
we have to talk about
mental disorders problems related to
mental health to get a little softer
someone will question their character
Ah I understand Isabela So it's not lack of
having something to do is a lack of
God Father Fábio has been dealing with
anxiety attacks for a long time Ah so I know
Isabela is lack of physical activity we
would not have athletes
manifesting the need for breaks in
some activities to preserve their
careers
one of our leading infectologists
in the country He said when he turned
70 that he thought B urnout had to
kill him
what do I have to do with it Isabela
the World Health Organization says
that one in four people will have
some problem related
to mental health throughout their lives we already live in
a period in which
occupational problems they were physical today, no one
questioned the use of a helmet
anymore, no one questions the use of ear protectors anymore,
but now we are talking about mental strength
and in this age of psychological safety that
I know that ANAC is moving
towards this environment of
psychological safety and this meeting is one of them
I have no doubt we need
communication
and communication needs to be very
clear
because if I say something, everyone will
have an interpretation
Let's give an example I'm going to say
a word here Mari you keep an eye on
me in the chat ok please And then I
need you to pay attention to this to
understand what a communication is Clara
I will say a word and you will
write in the chat the what this word
represents for you, say more table
just to remind you that the chat when she
says people is the slide, if you have
n't accessed it there, the
training portal has the link to the slide,
we're interacting there with
Isabela, ok so Isabela
let me know and I'll monitor the answers here, it
would be really cool if you could
participate I'll say a word and you
'll write what that word
means to you banana
write what you see
if no one has answered Mário it's
ok
[Music ]
there's music Banana is the fruit
we
go there
food
that's what I want Pepper
perfect breakfast fight
banana is
food what comes to mind people
is food fruit banana breakfast
banana is vitamin energy
Ah but obviously I said one something
you understood something else Did you
say it clearly Is what I'm
talking about here Is accessing
you clearly
So
see according to the National Association of
Occupational Medicine
Mental disorders are part of the
third cause of absence from
serious work,
so they hold this screen when you
see any unbelieving person, you
know, what they're feeling about what
this can cause
mental and behavioral disorders
are part of the third cause of
incapacity for work so
either I look at this information and
prevent
or I look at this information with the
eyes of an apprentice
eyes of a victim
outsourcing my responsibility
or attributing
your health to anyone other than you so I bring here a phrase
by doctor Ana Beatriz Barbosa Silva is
a very respected psychiatrist in the country
and she brings depression too much past
stress too much present anxiety
too much future as there won't be time
to talk about the three I'm going to focus on
anxiety
and what is leaving us in contexts
very challenging
that takes us away from ourselves and I'm
talking about sa people health is just going to give
time to talk to health I
would even like to talk about other things but
to what extent
absenteeism is the big problem
of
and of all the companies that I have
been visiting every day is it possible that
obsenteism is the problem or presenteeism
is a problem
because when I have a person
on leave he is in treatment when there
is a person in presenteeism he is
often unable to perform
tasks that compromise the lives of
thousands of people
who could not operate equipment and
so on So I need
understand that the only certainty I
have is uncertainty
We are just living one more
adaptation
ok
the car windshield is much bigger
than the rear view mirror
I look back to have references
but I need to look forward and the
steering is too much changes point this is
afact
so knowing this What
can I do look at all of Naque look a
lot at the sky look
when a storm is coming the
what's going on people I've done the
weather forecast many times ok so I'm
like this with you there I'm going to Observe if
the clouds are darkening if the wind has
changed direction If the leaves are
swaying a storm will come if
I'm going to close the window from my house or
not it's my decision
if I didn't close the window I got
home everything got wet it's
my responsibility you noticed What
are the external signs
Oh I understand Isabela is right What are the
internal signs because before my
Burnout I lived two years
ignoring all these
ignoring signs like that, actually
treating all of this but
individually without considering
the consequence that it would bring so
my body talked to me for two years
frequent headache
eye tremors nausea dizziness low immunity
bruxism stomach problem in the
intestine excessive sweating fall
hair stains on the skin tachycardia
shortness of breath swelling in the legs hormonal problems
Isabela I have a lot
after all that,
I started to sleep poorly
and those who sleep poorly live poorly
who sleeps less than 6 hours a night
is four times more likely to die
number of the Brazilian Sleep
Association is everything I'm talking about here people
is based on data and sources that I can share
with you after that I
started to have an anxiety crisis
memory pencil lack of concentration
after all that, that is, after my
body has already tried to warn me that, at this
rhythm, it is not possible
We are going down a path of
imbalance A storm
is coming then you didn't notice nervous breakdown
crying crisis isolation which is a
very
noticeable characteristic for those around but
sometimes it is difficult for those who are
living So what is the responsibility
you also have in realize the
changes in behavior of those
on your side
because after isolation or along with
isolation comes aggression
and my husband Mari is recorded in the tedex ok
people you can review this scene on the
internet with my husband came to me
and said like this Isabela is very
aggressive what I said to him
she is not aggressive
[Music]
then my record dropped and after that
Suicides came and went down then the we're
in Yellow September suicide prevention month
I don't prevent suicide by
promoting life
as
reminding you that those who think about
taking their own life don't want to get rid
of life, they want to get rid of a pain
those who think about taking their own life don't
wants to get rid of life wants to get rid of
a pain this sentence is not mine it's from
Major of the Fire Department Diógenes
Munhoz
so if I'm trying to get rid of a
pain in the wrong way with
Immediate rewards I'm not solving the
problem
they are playing problem under
the rug thinking that this will not
bring me consequences and a lot because
because of the image of these two handsome men is
superman super woman they convey to us
This illusion of that we can
with Immediate pleasures
neglect what we are feeling that
the body is saying
all this I'm talking about has to do
with some pain that you are experiencing
And then you can be an engineer, you can be a
mathematician, you can be a scientist, you can be a
physicist, astronomer, you can have a profession
whatever it is I'm talking to human
beings
and if we are human
we have very similar characteristics and
others very
different so it's very important to understand
What kind of excess are you experiencing if it's
excess work if it's excessive
physical activity be excess food and
the worst of all than
overconfidence because it's because of
overconfidence that I feed all
the other excesses and it's funny Mari
that we already look at the
car dashboard when the pointer is there to
reserve what you make you to
it's enough Ah but I Isabela when I
was 20 years old I was very
overconfident I got in the middle of the
way several times
even and
you remember what I'm going to say,
remember the pilot that was taking the
delegation from A Chapecoense
he thought it was going to get
there, so he didn't stop to fill up, In fact, he didn't
fill up before arriving
so look, I already have the resources to
see when I I need to stop a little
just to fill up people just to
fill up
it's not to give up on the trip it's not to
stop your plan it's not to leave
work it's just to fill up and we
'll get there well so after the
unsustainable lifestyle that I lived
I arrived at one in a movement that
is what I am bringing you here
because if we want a
sustainable world with sustainable resources
with sustainable production the word
sustainability is another one that was also
super trivialized because I am
living in an unsustainable way
for me Burnout is the absence of oneself
I'm so out of it that I don't have time to
stay in
so guys I need to bring you
a simple idea that sustainable productivity
how are you going
to be able to do what you do without
losing health in relationships
without anesthetics without amphetamines without drugs
without excessive drinking of other
anesthetics
so you know, right?
right
relationship problems but for me the worst
the worst loss when I talk about
relationships I get this absence
of self that will bring
health problems Isabela nice I understand the
problem that we are our
own saboteurs
wants to see how Mari you do it for
your oral hygiene
good
brush your teeth every day
after meals floss every
day every day after meals at
least three times you have to brush your
teeth right
who else at least every day this every
january is mine birthday then I
have a calendar of the dentist
without fail right to be able to do maintenance
and mine my annual technical stop
there at my check-up it's always in the middle of
my birthday that's beautiful what
day your birthday is the 28th aquariana
Okay now I understand
now
How beautiful what you said
you include yourself in your own agenda in the month
of your birthday it's like a
present, right, I'm going to the dentist
Look how far we've come, people, we
include ourselves in our own agenda, it seems something
extraordinary
And then Mari I ask you and for your
mental hygiene What do you do
to Isabela, this one I need a
little more discipline but I
every day This was a little before
coming to nac, it's during the
pandemic period that we were working
to keep the work
running and take care of people because I
work with people, right, we end up
accumulating a very big load, so
little before coming here i
started booking a time of day from
8 am to 9 am is the time
i have for myself so i go to the
gym or get a massage is a
time that I try to take is for me
not every day works Sometimes there are
unforeseen events but it is a time that I
have blocked in my schedule which is
my excellent time in the morning I loved
listening to you and then I bring you the
following idea
300 years
ago only 300 years ago It wasn't obvious like that
brushing your tooth every day a
toothbrush was used by all members of the
same family
serious serious today it's obvious to brush your
tooth every day before it's not
today we still see tooth care mental health, we are
still making this cut,
but just for you to understand what
affects mental health, we still see
it Mari as if it were something far away
expensive there when I take a vacation I
take care of myself, I'm not going to take a sabbatical or I
'm going to leave the my job is not people
mental hygiene is like oral hygiene is
every day it's an individual decision And then
I'm going to bring you something
amazing attention to the screen print the
five janitors of the mind
because then May when we and if you
meet again I'll tell you like this
Mário what are you doing for your
mental health then you will tell me what
is being possible
sleep hygiene food
physical activity and time for leisure and family
serious Isabela seriously every day
is a decision that now you're going to take it and
I'm going to say it with lots of love The
other day I was in the
ultra modern laboratory thinks that
science fiction laboratory talking
to
pharmaceutical scientists physicists then a
person asked about me but the beauty
how am i going to have time to sleep
Look what we are discussing
we are talking about negotiation for
you to preserve your sleep time your
hygiene and food time three
basic things
And why am I talking about this in
Yellow September in this meeting with
you because it is precisely what is
essential we go Giving up when the
schedule is too full or when I want to
embrace the world and do everything it
's just when you want to embrace the
world that If you don't have your hug
if you sleep poorly you live badly if you
give up your hygiene and your
food it's no use having
time management tools because you already have the
main tool for
time management invented a long time ago is the
watch everyone has a watch does
n't I just need to bring
elements here for you to include yourself in your
own agenda to prevent not only
Burnout but other health
or relationship problems so now
look at the time update identity
for me it is
the first step that we all have to take
to recognize and accept that the cycle is
over what is working now
what is no longer what i
have strengths what i do not have
so i can recognize
toxic behaviors
smoking for 70 years didn't hurt today
nobody accepts Santa Claus
coming to our house
trying to multitask people is the biggest
trap
they put us because it gets more tired
stress favors mistakes
decrease creativity everything we don't
want so if you try to do two
intellectual things at the same time it
will go wrong you can print this screen
send it to Amiga send it to Zap send it to the
family send the link of this
meeting and then how is it I will
recognize toxic
behaviors my toxic behaviors only have one
way
self-knowledge
when I interviewed your Abílio Diniz
he told me Isabella I could only deal
with all the challenges of my life with
therapy
I started before 30 years old and today people
are over 80 and It's
booming, right? In a good way, with ideas and
health,
so I can't go to the market and
talk gives me a kilo of self-knowledge, in
fact, it gives me about 10, right, because if I
attend a lecture there the other day and the
girl reminded me that we change the
all the time
print this screen and answer for you
with the help of your therapist whoever
you want
today What are your basic needs
today today me Isabela I need to sleep for
8 hours when I was in my early 20s
Bá could sleep 4 hours the next
day I was thinking I was Powerful I didn't sleep at all
and I'm fine with time this changes
How is your health your exams
are up to
date Isabela but then again I don't have
health insurance or it's too expensive
it's your health
so we tend to think everything
we're going to do for ourselves is expensive but for
home, buy wallpaper, change the sofa,
right shoes, clothes the immediate rewards
when we're tired girls
we solve our tiredness by sleeping we're not
buying a bag a a a a treat But
that's what we do when we don't have it
when we don't know each other when we
don't realize what is really going to affect
our health so everything you do is in
your favor o that it is negotiable and
non-negotiable today people yesterday I had an
incredible lesson with Dona Mariana
we were lining up this meeting here
she said like this people I need to go there and
pick up my children This
is negotiable pa for me my
sleep is negotiable but for each there
is a negotiable i
like that is more coherent now right
so i need to
answer the question one two three four
five six to know what that can be
delegated because if i take everything to
If I overload my back, in
addition to muscle pain, I will be
very irritated because I won't be
able to handle everything And then only by
organizing
yourself will you have
appropriate reactions for each situation remember
what I said about the cockroach is an example but
how many times are we in front of an
ant reacting as if we were in
front of a lion
So these are situations that will generate
a type of stress if it will be
positive or chronic adaptive is an individual analysis
And then I as a leader as a manager I
need to see that my reactions can
generate interpretations
I train leaders on what abuse is
because there are people who are committing
abuse and harassment and don't know that it's
an ab moral psychological use
So you are solely responsible for
realizing how you affect your health and
the people
in your environment So how you deal with
the daily ups and downs of everyday life
has to do
with maintaining your health because if
you don't deal well with the highs and
lows you are living in
chronic stress and chronic stress brings
dozens of problems Burnout
how am I going to solve this story
including myself in my own agenda so
I can wear the company's shirt you can
Of course as long as you too Wear your
pajamas
just like that because if I sleep badly I
think badly if I'm giving up
sleep time in my schedule to the
detriment of work I'll tell
you the medium long term you're going to have
to give up your schedule because You
're not
healthy that's what happened to me when I
thought that
doing all the shifts, right, they made me
available all the time, wouldn't bring me
consequences. So
we need to include it in the p own agenda
sleep and hygiene nutrition these
movements so that relationships
don't affect your productivity
simple like that ah Isabela But it's hard,
right, if including yourself in your own agenda
is a decision
personal and professional goals because
you'll have to
choose what you're going to stress about
. that you are going to wear out we
are talking about health maintenance here
so you will have to have elements
to keep your energies energy with the
unforeseen wants to see a more
perfect example than this
Yesterday we managed to cross the agendas
to be together today
someone you can see this as unforeseen or
with an opportunity I saw it as a
great opportunity So not every
unforeseen is bad just as not every
invitation is an opportunity
I will only know how to differentiate one from the other
if I am in dynamic balance If
I am sleeping well eating
well with the hygiene time to know
what is coherent or not so today I
Isabela gave up my there is
physical activity to be with you
consciously because my purpose is to
take this information to prevent
any consequences that are bad
for the excesses
suicide is one of them so I need to
ask for help I need to delegate I
need to let go so that I have
value in my time we are talking
here about psychological safety which was a
term created by midwanderson author of
this book that I highly recommend that
talks about the psychological safety environment
in which I can express myself
interact learn and belong without fear
of consequences and I know that
you have here a very interesting people management,
right in what Mrs. Bianca
Fi uses that today she is wearing Red Lipstick
she is not showing up here but I've
seen she
even participated in the hiring of
many of you it's been a long time she
can
direct you to the best path
because oh people fix the roof
before the rain
I only preserve my health
when I am healthy and
Don't wait for rain to fix the
roof so one thing is an environment of
psychological safety the movement that the
company's culture is making for
change this is medium and long term
but everyone has their responsibility
to seek help and
I'm feeling there's a leak here I'm going to
wait for the bad no I'm going to share
this wheel of life with you because it's the
best way for you to have
a picture of your moment
Where is the imbalance what
you can or can't
adjust I'm talking about adjustment people and
we can only
draw up a good flight plan for our
lives when we have information from the
sky when we have information from the
atmosphere it is not I need my
information to draw up my plan
So here is the wheel of life later I
share it in link also so
you can access ending here
Mário for us to open so for
our discussion right here
with our time I need to observe the
s internal and external signals
Ah but I still think all of this
is silly, it's a decision so we
need to be proud of the path we've
traced so far so pride in the
past but humility for the future with
an apprentice's eyes I need to slow down
a little
to continue the movement to
keep accelerating this sign is not
on the decorative road
it means that if you
exceed your limit you put yourself
at risk in other people too so
I need to stop a little bit I'm
telling no one your jobs people I'm
talking look if you already fill this wheel of
life I'm already happy with life because then
you go, each one with your own, each one will
recognize Where you are imbalance
so I finish here thanking you so much for
your time leaving here three just
put my name on YouTube that will
appear a lot of content but in these
three specifically I delve into
this that I commented with you in my
book to give you a break on how to find a
limit in this world without limits Mary
now gives the floor to you so
we can exchange a little more
Hi Isabela how valuable all this
you brought to us I'm here
following the comments a slide
your talk your speech moved we
have people posting comments here
who were very touched that they saw in
their families or in themselves
situations that you are
needed I will condense that some
comments on two fronts there was a
comment there early on asking
if women are more likely to
have mental health problems is colleague
man who said no I went through it
actually I think that only women
talk more about this subject than
men so there is this gender issue
that I wish you could
eventually address that with us, right, the
agency has a characteristic that I
mentioned this with you yesterday right We
have a male majority Here
we have around 75% of men
contracts with 25% of the staff women
and another point that was and here I
include myself ok because we who occupy
leadership roles occupy
leadership positions and we have to have the police
take care of ourselves with our own health But
we are responsible for a team and
taking care of a team is not it's just the result
of the work of these people but also of
sustainability, right, of ensuring that
these people stay well and manage to
work balancing the personal and
professional side and some comments came
here on the issue of how to
sensitize managers how to make
the people who occupy a position managers
do not value productivity or
Any Cost that they can perceive is
how to make someone who is in
a leadership position sensitive, it is a
colleague who is in need of help, not
necessarily he has a medical certificate,
but in a situation to
identify and be able to support your
teams I will continue reading slide but
already raise these two balls here if you
can addressing
Obri Thanks for all the comments I
'm also watching here but I'll leave it
to Mário to bring that
comment that you see the most that can
serve more people well
first thing
this conversation is going on it is a good
start that there is a movement to
psychological safety and I can only
mobilize my leadership my leadership by
communicating then the main tool of
this New Age of psychological safety
since
mental health problems are now taking the same
place as physical health problems
I need to communicate
this sometimes boss isn't
realizing what's going on either so
i need to speak up
oh but it's obvious he's
overloading me no it
's not so there needs to be
two-way communication
oh but i'm afraid of what this could
happen if you don't try you
won't know if you don't manifest a pain
especially those that are invisible
i have no way of knowing me as a leader
Ah but he knows why he or
she is putting me in a situation
like this or that I will repeat it is not obvious
that each one is trying to survive with
their resources in the best way and each
one within their own home since you now have a
lot of autonomy and flexibility
are very different and very
challenging contexts so don't count on this
Ah but it's so obvious no it's not
after that there's another element that is
when it stops being invisible when
it becomes invisible so observe
behaviors When the person doesn't open
the camera first thing when the person
is more aggressive when he is isolating himself
this person needs help Ah but
then how do I help go to the
mall it will be that we are not going
anywhere let's talk first
right it's not with shopping it's not with drinks
no It's with drugs that we're going to solve
the pain it's with conversation Ah but then
who can I talk to I don't
trust anyone
Look I won't be here if Dona Bianca
wants and use made me sure that she has been
working with you for a long time many of
you know her
bianca.umas@anac.gov.br is Bianca will
address you to the right person
because also but we want to talk And
then want to talk about any It
's not like that anywhere either,
every thing in its place I know it's
challenging for the teams and I also know
it's challenging for the leaders
as we are going to find a way by
talking because the context within
ANAC may have different characteristics
from other companies but I, Isabela, know
that overload has
universal consequences,
just like a bridge when it is built
and it has a lot of weight on top of it, it breaks
anywhere in the world
so it is necessary to communicate I answered the
question Mário
answered yes Isabela and I wanted to highlight
here for you guys if you're already
going through a difficult situation, have you
tried to talk to your boss and see
the comment on islador here? What if I
already talked to my boss? If this was not
effective I would like to highlight Isabela
that the superintendence of
people management is here to help the
servers and the leaders so I
want to talk here with you who are
watching us if you have someone on
your team who is difficult to you deal with
you that I have a leadership car
you don't know how to help someone on your
team who is apparently going through
a difficult period call us and
we will help you and
guide you on how to deal with the person
who is in your team if you are the
opposite, if not another perspective,
you try to seek help, you are trying to
improve, you are trying to communicate with
your boss, this is not reverberating, it
also brings us this issue that
we are here both to support the
leaders and to take care of people
so Bianca is in charge here of the
team that deals with this topic and we
are delicate situations of course you are
not going to use a channel as SGP answers
that it is our channel of doubts for the
work of managing day-to-
day people are sensitive personal issues and
we are here to help
you I also personally make myself
available for us to talk now
Isabela we don't want you to get to
that point, right when we are already
suffering physically or mentally, it
means that the subject is already gringolous, right?
So I wanted to say how we
prevent not only when we already reach a point
of Suicidal thinking pawn, as you
commented that it was an extreme point there
that what happened to you is that thank
God you are being treated right you were
able to wake up and wake up to this
for a new journey right it
means work in your life I
wanted to ask you who came here
on the slider how do we balance
you made a comment there in the
lecture that we set aside time for us to
look for those five pillars of
Health he made the check list there and I had
contact with the wheel of life for the first
time
2015 and I apply the wheel of life every
beginning of the year at the turn of my
new year you know when you make the
new year's plans I fill out my wheel of
life I keep the history and it changes right it's
all too much changes but in addition to
filling in and doing self-knowledge,
there are some practical tips there for
people who want to have a good performance who
want to deliver are committed because
our lives and work are part
of our identity when we love
what we do we don't want to be
mediocre, right, we want to do a
job of excellence there is this
characteristic There are many people who are
passionate about aviation who are
passionate about what they do They are people who are
very critical and who want to have an
excellent performance, but how
can we achieve excellence with
sustainability help me here by giving
some recaps here of what you
said things that people take
from here and don't forget practical tips
ok laughing well Yes or no Yes ok No
because there's not enough time why
What's contributing to you not
having time can be delegated someone can
do it you can ask someone for help
Ah but that person doesn't do it like me it's
you who is loading it
first thing is sleeping well Yes or
no
second thing is having time to
feed yes or no Yes ok No because it
does not have time because what is
happening around it that does not
allow you to guarantee time to eat
third thing is managing to wash your
hair girls or are living with
ponytails this video Mário has 6
million views on Tik Tok because I
know what I'm talking about because I know
that when we are going down a
path of tiredness and exhaustion we
go Giving up our hygiene boys
stop cutting their hair shaving
girls stop washing their hair
stop doing their nails which are details that
seem like vanity to some but what I know
is a lack of false self-care I have to include
in your own agenda with what I'm going to only you
can do for you and This demonstrates the
excess of activities So how do
I deal with the excess of activities
delegating
arriving Ah but Isabela this is difficult
I can only include my own agenda
training people challenging because it's been
years thinking differently so
I need to choose Do you know how many
choices we make a day
35 thousand
from the time we open our eyes to the time
we close our eyes right from the time
we wake up to the time we wake up we sleep
35 minutes and that are decisions such as
sleep an extra minute or not turn on the
side move my hair I tie my hair
Put on that blue scarf or don't ask the
question or not 35 minutes we're
choosing all the time
even more for those who try
multitasking, right, because it alternates attention,
so Mário I need to choose,
I could bring you other information here,
but as I said, it
is essential that we are Giving up
and that makes management We still need to negotiate
what should be non-negotiable
ok so
Hi sorry we have two more
minutes here with you before we
start saying goodbye and Carla is
remembering here on the slide what we
skipped the gender issue you see the
difference between boys and girls here
in relation to let's go women are more
likely and diagnoses
are more it doesn't mean that men don't
have
them women take care of themselves more because they
go to the gynecologist more, right the men
go there to the urologist especially
now with Blue November campaigns of
integral health and such but there are two reasons
that women have more so in fact
three one is that it is more diagnosed
because because it goes to the doctor
more often
the second answer is related to
this Because women have
hormonal fluctuations that biologically I don't
need to explain for you women
have more hormonal oscillations I had
last week with Dr Jairo Bauer a
psychiatrist and he said no I need to
explain more that women have more
hormonal oscillations this is a fact as
I deal with this fact accepting and
seeking resources to deal with it in the best
way so first thing
women go to the doctor more second
thing she has more normal oscillations and
third thing
it has been so many centuries not being able to occupy
certain spaces that now the woman
occupies all she wants so we
learn to accumulate tasks and now
we need to learn to divide tasks
so because of the double triple shift
we accumulate more tasks so it is
also our responsibility to ask more
help whether you will have this help or not
will depend on your patience in asking for the
same thing in different ways
is Isabela so we receive some
comments here in the is from experiences that
have already happened things that have happened and
that mark us right then we had
comments here from colleagues who spoke
a while ago I went through a
period of great suffering So much
overload that still leaves marks on me,
others said I was happy to
talk and I felt stigmatized, right or
is it that I feel that at the agency I get
stamped if I go through a problem
such as we break this
stigma but how is it that we
take care of rehabilitation knows because there comes
a time that if we go through a
period of suffering I feel that there is no
help is bad and feeling that there is no way out of
this suffering is even worse, you know, how
can we
take this load off this stigma and
helping people to see that there is a FD
that you can be happy with after a
difficult episode that has
the best chapter and that
we can finally have light at the end of the tunnel, right,
how do we do that, helps me
here really trying to bring changes
to organize, hey, Mari, I'm going with this
answer of mine, saying goodbye to you, it's
because of the time I'm going to catch a flight,
okay, people in half an hour, so that's really
why I can't go on anymore
and your answer is not so simple I would
need more than an hour to
start this
literacy that we are talking about here
is education and health
education we don't educate anyone in
an hour but I manage to stimulate
interest so that everyone can go deeper
into it that caught the most attention
How can I reduce stigma by
talking
not judging not reducing pain
first thing
then First me then the other I
'm judging Someone has a
stop behavior when someone
comes to tell me something how
am I acting it
's with these people who are asking me for
help because people too, we
always put ourselves as we need help
but sometimes we also receive
requests for help How am I putting myself
I know no I don't know
how to deal with it I need to address
And then therapy The Psychologist the
general practitioner a specialist who has a
different skill than yours is the one who will be
able to treat what you are feeling in the best way.
I don't care for Isabela but I think therapy
is really silly, it's the same thing as
having a toothache and refusing
remember it wasn't always like this before the
dentist it was probably also seen
as unnecessary today it's not anymore So
this is the only way Mário is
self-knowledge I can do this journey
alone or accompanied by a
professional who has more skills
than me to organize simple ideas
as well as how can I include myself in my
own agenda,
excluding what is no longer useful, which is
why identity updating is
essential for that you exclude
what no longer fits in this lifestyle
that today you have one of the great
dissatisfactions of our life is wanting to
handle today's agenda with the
characteristics we had in the past
without recognizing the strengths and
weaknesses then it really can see the Pope
say that it won't help Mari
Isabela wonderful I know you have a
schedule thank you very much for your
words for comparing sharing with you all
this experience is personal we stay
here I want to remember that we
have more Yellow September programming
Don't miss it we continue this dialogue
right an opening that for us to be able to
bring more quality of life even
to our work this moment that
we are working hybrid a lot of
people in remote work without these
boundaries between personal life and
professional life is a learning experience for us
but I'm sure that this
flexibility and autonomy that we have
to work at the agency brings much
more benefits for us than
harm And these difficult issues
we will learn and we will work
together we are here to look
forward, right that the rear view serves as
lessons and that we improve and
manage to build the agency that we
want to work on day to day day each one there
with their own inside their square, right
doing their best in their surroundings with
the people they live with is ca give a one
there bringing the change that we want to
see right ahead so Isabela is
that my thanks I loved meeting you
I hope we have other events
in the future I wish you a good
trip and Success always Thank you guys
a hug and thank you
to all a hug